<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>pedmiston.org</title><link href="http://pedmiston.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://pedmiston.org/feeds/unsolicited.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://pedmiston.org/</id><updated>2014-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>NHST Quotes</title><link href="http://pedmiston.org/nhst-quotes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Pierce Edmiston</name></author><id>tag:pedmiston.org,2014-03-06:nhst-quotes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not making some nit-picking statistician's correction. I am saying that the whole business is so radically defective as to be scientifically almost pointless (Meehl, 1978, p. 823).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; values are like mosquitoes. They have an evolutionary niche somewhere and no amount of scratching, swatting, or spraying will dislodge them (Campbell, 1982, p. 698).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the problems of statistical induction, we must finally rely, as have the older sciences, on replication (Cohen, 1994, p. 1002).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many observers have noted the failure of psychology as a cumulative science. Although many reasons can be advanced for this problem, perhaps the most important is the ... dichotomous interpretation of significance levels, resulting in over reliance on &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; values as the main evidence contained in a study (Rossi, 1997, p. 175). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is time for researchers to avail themselves of the full arsenal of quantitative and qualitative statistical tools... The current practice of focusing exclusively on a dichotomous reject-nonreject decision strategy of null hypothesis testing can actually impede scientific progress... The focus of research should be on ... what data tell us about the magnitude of effects, the practice significance of effects, and the steady accumulation of knowledge (Kirk, 2003, p. 100).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished Cumming's book today, and he listed the above quotes near the end. He claims to have not been able to find any in defense of NHST; I'll punt on that one. I never know how to interpret decades-old debates like those surrounding &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; values, which is why I like the mosquitoes one so much. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More stats quotes here: &lt;a href="http://warnercnr.colostate.edu/~anderson/nester.html"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="statistics"></category><category term="quotes"></category></entry><entry><title>Blurring the line</title><link href="http://pedmiston.org/blurring-the-line.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Pierce Edmiston</name></author><id>tag:pedmiston.org,2014-02-24:blurring-the-line.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year's &lt;a href="http://edge.org/"&gt;Edge.org&lt;/a&gt; annual question is: What scientific idea is ready for retirement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Holcombe's answer is relevant to a discussion we've been having in our lab about open science, replicability, and preregistration, and is neatly argued. I highly suggest &lt;a href="http://edge.org/response-detail/25445"&gt;it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex's answer for a scientific idea that is ready for retirement is that "Science is self-correcting." He writes, "Self-correction is thus undermined by several factors, some very human, and some simply institutional," and points to changing the culture associated with publishing null findings and expanding the peer review process as ways to combat the statistically inevitable bias in [psychology's] publication record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way I’ve been thinking about it lately: publication bias, researcher degrees of freedom, etc., these reflect a &lt;strong&gt;blurring of the line&lt;/strong&gt; between argument and persuasion. As my advisor Gary Lupyan said in a recent, relevant discussion: No data in psychology stands for itself. Abstracts aren't tables of statistics and citations are not determined by effect sizes. When we report multiply interpretable results, we are arguing|persuading our audience to see the results "our way." The publication bias--that we only publish positive results--reflects the fact that positive results are more persuasive than negative results. Researcher degrees of freedom--that undisclosed analysis techniques abolish the validity of null hypothesis significance testing--reflect the fact that a cleaner story makes for a cleaner interpretation of the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If data in psychology is multiple interpretable, how do we stick to argument and not to persuasion? Preregistration seems to be a viable option. Preregistration in its many forms is a way to tie our hands behind our backs: "If I’m going to trick you / If we find ourselves in the impossible circumstance that I am wrong about this, I’m going to be wrong about this for reasons we can all agree on."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm often struck by the pessimism of the argument (that we need structural change in order to assure ourselves that we aren't unintentionally misleading each other), but if scientists are supposed to be anything, aren’t we supposed to be pessimists-eternal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will say, however, I think Alex’s title answer "Science is self-correcting" as his example of a scientific idea ready for retirement is misleading. To say that science is self-correcting is a tautology, and it shouldn't be retired as much as it should be focused on or returned to. It’s the other crap that needs to go, not the idea that experiments are reliable data-generators even if our understanding of them may change. It reminds me of a quip by Sanjay Srivastava:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;Science is not self-correcting, say scientists correcting science

— Sanjay Srivastava (@hardsci) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hardsci/statuses/392327064402939904"&gt;October 21, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="openscience"></category><category term="preregristration"></category><category term="edge"></category></entry><entry><title>Ideas</title><link href="http://pedmiston.org/quote-ideas.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Pierce Edmiston</name></author><id>tag:pedmiston.org,2014-02-23:quote-ideas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Roger Sperry in "Mind, brain, and humanist values" (1965):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideas cause ideas and help evolve new ideas. They interact with each other and with other mental forces in the same brain, in neighboring brains, and, thanks global communication, in far distant, foreign brains. And they also interact with the external surroundings to produce &lt;em&gt;in toto&lt;/em&gt; a burstwise advance in evolution that is far beyond anything to hit the evolutionary scene yet, including the emergence of the living cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="ideas"></category><category term="evolution"></category></entry></feed>